Preliminary Guide to the Watson Fredericks Kinney Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Watson Fredericks Kinney collection
1876-1995
1876-1928
MS 1584
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(3 boxes, 1 folio)
The collection consists of Kinney family correspondence, genealogical material, a memoir, a writing on the icaroscope, and a report on a Yale engineering inspection trip.
Kinney, Watson Fredericks, 1906-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Watson F. Kinney and transferred from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1989, 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Watson Fredericks Kinney was born on December 25, 1906, in Lock Haven, Pennsylvania, son of James Montrose Kinney and Helen Watson Fredericks Kinney. His father was president of the Kinney-Coons Company, Inc. of Yonkers, New York.
Kinney attended Pelham High School and Phillips-Andover. He studied mechanical engineering at the Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University. His Yale relatives include two uncles, Gilmore Kinney, '07S and Orson A. Kinney, '18.
After graduation from Yale in 1929, Kinney joined the Detroit Edison Company as an engineer in the production department. He was owner of the Watson F. Kinney Sales Engineering Company in Detroit, Michigan from 1958 until his retirement in 1974.
(Extracted from: History of the Class of Nineteen Hundred Twenty-Nine, Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, vol. 1, 1929.
50 Year Record, Yale '29, 1979.)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Kinney family correspondence, genealogical material, a memoir, a writing on the icaroscope, and a report on a Yale engineering inspection trip.
Engineering; Spanish-American War, 1898; Philippines; West (U.S.); Kinney, Watson Fredericks, 1906-; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School
- Original Accession, Accession 1990-M-042
  Scope and Contents
  Received from: Watson F. Kinney, 1989 July 1, transferred from Beinecke Rare Book Library
  .75 linear feet (2 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Correspondence of Benjamin Irving Kinney (primarily from Cuba), 1895 Mar, 1901 February-April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of James Montrose Kinney, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of Gilmore Kinney, Sr., 1904 June-Aug, 1910 October-November (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of Gilmore Kinney, Jr. from the Brunn-Kinney Co., 1910 March-April (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence of Henry Judd Gray to Benjamin Kinney, 1927-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kinney family history, typescript photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Typescript of My Two Boys, by Gilmore Kinney, Sr., with accompanying photocoies, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 9)
  - Memorabilia
    - Denver and Rio Grande dining car menu, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gift list, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1922 March 21-22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yale Engineering Inspection Trip, report by Watson F. Kinney, 1929 March 27-April 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The Story of the Icaroscope," by Watson F. Kinney [the instrument used to observe and record the detonation of the atomic bomb in Operation Crossroads at Bikini Atoll in the Pacific Ocean on 1946 Jul 1], [1995]; shelved with box 2 of Accession 90-M-042 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Land grant certificates of Kansas properties, 1876, 1883, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Photograph of "Dewey's Return Home", 1899 September 29 (Box 3)
- Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-028
  - Memoirs of Operation Crossroads, by Watson F. Kinney [the story of atomic bomb testing at Bikini Atoll in the Pacific Ocean on 1946 Jul 1], [1995?] (Box 1, Folder 1)